Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (CSLEA) Records
Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (CSLEA) Records
1951-1969
Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults
45.5 linear ft.
Established by a grant from the Fund for Adult Education in 1951, the Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (CSLEA) worked with universities seeking to initiate or to improve adult education programs. Its purpose was to help American higher education develop greater effectiveness and a deeper sense of responsibility for the liberal education of adults. During its tenure the Center had three directors; John S. Diekhoff (1952-1953), John B. Schwertman (1953-1956), and A.A. Liveright (1956-1968). The records include correspondence, organizational files, publication files, writings, and miscellany. Key correspondents, mostly from the Center, are James T. Carey, Alexander N. Charters, Roger DeCrow, John S. Diekhoff, C. Scott Fletcher, Freda H. Goldman, Morton Gordon, Kenneth Haygood, Cyril Orvin Houle, A. A. Liveright, Harry L. Miller, John B. Schwertman, Peter E. Siegle, Marilyn M. Vaughan, and James B. Whipple.
148890
Biographical History
The Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (CSLEA) was established in 1951 with a grant from the Fund for Adult Education (FAE) that had been awarded on the basis of a proposal submitted by the Committee on Liberal Education of the Association of University Evening Colleges. Throughout its history the Center's primary source of financial support was the FAE. Established to work with universities seeking to initiate or to improve adult education programs, the Center's general purpose was to help American higher education develop greater effectiveness and a deeper sense of responsibility for the liberal education of adults. The Center fulfilled this purpose of working with university adult education administration through Center projects, consultation services of the Center staff, four publication series (Notes and Essays, Reports, Research Reports, and Occasional Papers), a semi-monthly newsletter, Continuing Education for Adults, which contained information gathered from the field, and services of the Center clearinghouse on adult education information.
The Center produced experimental study-discussion guides for adult use in evening colleges and later shifted focus by studying the quality of administrative leadership, faculty performance, and status of continuing education in colleges and universities. Increasingly the Center's activities concerned national leadership conferences, the development of special degree programs specifically for adults, and seminars for faculty, deans, and presidents. Its research resulted in an extensive and influential list of publications. The Center also made numerous small "seed" grants to try out experimental ideas. In 1956, upon formal invitation, the Center's services were extended to the institutions of the National University Extension Association. In 1958 it began to work with a special committee of black colleges and universities and in 1959 with a newly formed Committee on Liberal Education of the Association of American Colleges. Thus the Center's work of liberally oriented higher education for adults had spread across the spectrum of higher education. CSLEA was also influential in the development of international adult education, providing the International Congress of University Adult Education with a secretariat during its formative years.
James B. Whipple points out in his history of the Center that the distinguishing characteristics of the Center included its quasi-independence. The Center was established on the campus of the University of Chicago, but remained independent of that institution. From 1964 until its termination in 1968, the Center was affiliated with Boston University but retained its independence. There were three directors of the Center:
John Simeon Diekhoff, 1952-1953
John B. Schwertman, 1953-1956
Alexander Albert Liveright, 1956-1968
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (CSLEA) Records are arranged in five series: correspondence, organizational files, publication files, writings, and miscellany. The inclusive dates of the collection are 1951-1969; the 1969 materials consists exclusively of correspondence dealing with the termination of the Center. Besides correspondence, the collection contains printed material including dittoed and mimeographed material, published material, periodical and newspaper clippings, some computer print-outs and galley proofs, typescript copy of material published by the CSLEA, and financial material. The categories of correspondence and organizational files contain 78% of the material in the collection.
Correspondence contains incoming and outgoing letters from 1951 to 1969. Incoming letters are arranged ahead of paired outgoing letters, regardless of which ones are the responses. Arrangement is chronological according to the date of the letter or the date of the incoming letter where two or more letters are attached. Undated correspondence is located at the end of the category. Correspondence dated only to the year is placed at the end of the year folder, and correspondence dated only to the month is placed at the end of that month. Correspondents include members of the CSLEA staff, members of the Center's board of directors, key staff members of the Fund for Adult Educatiobn, as well as administrators of adult education programs throughout the country and staff members of other adult education organizations. Correspondents significant for the volume of their letters, their authority with and within CSLEA, and/or the subject matter of their letters, include the following:
Carey, James T.
Charters, Alexander N.
DeCrow, Roger
Diekhoff, John Simeon
Fletcher, C. Scott
Goldman, Freda H.
Gordon, Morton
Haygood, Kenneth
Houle, Cyril Orvin
Liveright, Alexander Albert
Miller, Harry L.
Schwertman, John B.
Sheats, Paul H.
Seigle, Peter E.
Vaughan, Marilyn M.
Whipple, James B.
Organizational files of CSLEA are divided into administrative, financial, legal, and project categories.
Administrative files contain board of directors meeting reports, meeting files, memoranda, personnel files, general reports, and staff files. Board of directors meetings from 1951 to 1967 generated agendas, minutes, and meeting reports. Meeting files include material dealing with meetings of bodies within CSLEA, meetings sposored by the Center, and meetings not held under the Center's auspices but attended by CSLEA staff members. Other files were generated by the annual CSLEA staff meetings. Among the minutes are informal reports of meetings, as well as recorded and approved minutes and minutes of staff meetings from 1951 to 1967. There are resolutions passed at meetings, conference proceedings, and transcripts. There are memoranda that are often staff reports on Center projects, institutional visits, conferences, and interviews. These memoranda, by their individual and collective bulk and for their wide range of content, detailed information, and sometime confidential nature, provide an important source concerning the activities and philosophy of the Center. Personnel files, general reports, and staff files complete the administrative section of organizational files.
Financial data include proposed budgets, an accounts payable and receivable journal, cash receipts and disbursement journals, payroll records, compensation vouchers, payroll checks, bank statements, auditor's reports, income tax records, salary lists, petty cash records, and bank signature authorizations.
Legal files consist primarily of articles, agreements, and by-laws.
Projects files complete the organizational category and make up the largest part of the collection. These folders relate to various projects, including conferences, workshops, institutes, and meetings, as well as grants for basic support of CSLEA and its programs. Although it includes reports and proposals both by and to CSLEA, the bulk of the material was prepared by CSLEA. Reports include staff reports on Center projects, research, and institutional visits, as well as committee reports and Center reports to the Fund for Adult Education. In addition to more formal reports and proposals, these files include general material dealing with areas of interest to CSLEA, listed by subject. Several of the more important groups of material are the Carey Study (the Center's report of AUEC and NUEA to the Fund), the Arts Project, the Evaluation Project, Liberal Education for Specialists (Operation Micro), Negro College Program, the Leadership Conferences of CSLEA, and special degree programs. The folders are arranged alphabetically by project titles.
Publication files include brochures, curriculum materials, publication lists and schedules, and material relating to the CSLEA newsletter. The group of adult education curricular materials prepared by the CSLEA staff dates mostly from 1951 and 1952. This material is arranged chronologically, with undated material placed at the end of the group.
Writings are divided into two sections: addresses, and articles and books. Notable authors include A. A. Liveright and James B. Whipple, former assistant director of the Center and author of its history. Addresses includes speeches delivered by members of CSLEA, by non-CSLEA personnel at meetings sponsored by CSLEA, as well as speeches dealing with subjects of interest to the Center. Addresses are arranged alphabetically by author, with unidentified authors placed at the end. The date given for an address may be the date it was typed, but it is more often the date it was delivered. Ar ticles and books contains manuscripts of CSLEA staff and board of directors, consultants to the Center, and, in a few cases, students of Liveright. Also here are manuscripts of books published by CSLEA, some of them written or edited by members of the Center's staff. The arrangement of the drafts of these books does not necessarily correspond to their order of revision. However, where there are large-format typescript printer's copies of manuscripts, these are identified as the last draft. Material is arranged alphabetically by author or editor, and the manuscripts of each individual are arranged alphabetically by title. Manuscripts, the authors of which are unidentified, are placed at the end of the group. The date given for each article is generally the date it was typed. For books the date is either the publication or copyright date.
Miscellany is arranged by type. Brochures and announcements include descriptions of the Center and its programs. Reprints of articles by CSLEA staff members are arranged chronologically. Periodical clippings of articles by CSLEA staff members or about the Center are arranged chronologically. Newspaper clippings, also arranged chronologically, contain articles about the Center and its activities.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing of all adult education collections. In particular, see also the following:
Organizations
Association of University Evening Colleges (AUEC) Records
Fund for Adult Education (FAE) Records
International Congress of University Adult Education (ICUAE) Records
National University Extension Association (NUEA) Records
Individuals
Alexander N. Charters Papers
A.A. Liveright Papers
George A. Parkinson Papers
Paul H. Sheats Papers
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults -- Archives.; Carey, James T., 1925-; Charters, Alexander N.; DeCrow, Roger.; Fletcher, Cyril Scott, 1904-; Goldman, Freda H.; Gordon, Morton, 1933-; Haygood, Kenneth.; Houle, Cyril Orvin, 1913-; Liveright, A. A. (Alexander Albert), 1907-; Miller, Harry L., 1920-; Sheats, Paul H., 1907-1984.; Whipple, James B.; Diekhoff, John S.; Schwertman, John B.; Siegle, Peter E.; Vaughan, Marilyn M.; Adult education -- United States.; Education -- Curricula.; Education -- United States.; Education, Humanistic.; Evening and continuation schools.; Universities and colleges -- United States.; Announcements.; Agendas (administrative records); Articles.; Books.; Brochures.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Financial records.; Legal files.; Manuscripts for publication.; Minutes (administrative records); Pamphlets.; Reports.; Speeches (documents); Adult education
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Various sources, including transfer from University Archives, gift of B.J. Vaughn, gift of CSLEA.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - 1951, Mar-Dec, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1952, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - 1953, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1954, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - 1955, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - 1956, Jan-Sep, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - 1956, Oct-Dec (Box 3)
  - 1957, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - 1958, Jan-Jul, 7 folders (Box 3)
  - 1958, Aug-Dec, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - 1959, Jan-Jul, 7 folders (Box 4)
  - 1959, Aug-Dec, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - 1960, Jan-May, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - 1960, Jun-Dec, 7 folders (Box 6)
  - 1961, Jan-Feb, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - 1961, Mar-Oct, 8 folders (Box 7)
  - 1961, Nov-Dec, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - 1962, Jan-Jun, 6 folders (Box 8)
  - 1962, Jul-Dec, 6 folders (Box 9)
  - 1963, Jan-Feb, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - 1963, Mar-Oct, 8 folders (Box 10)
  - 1963, Nov-Dec, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - 1964, Jan-Feb, 4 folders (Box 11)
  - 1964, Mar-Jun, 5 folders (Box 12)
  - 1964, Jul-Dec, 6 folders (Box 13)
  - 1965, Jan (to Jan 15) (Box 13)
  - 1965, Jan (from Jan 16)-May, 7 folders (Box 14)
  - 1965, Jun-Oct, 5 folders (Box 15)
  - 1965, Nov-Dec, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - 1966, Jan-Feb, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - 1966, Mar-Aug, 6 folders (Box 17)
  - 1966, Sep-Dec, 4 folders (Box 18)
  - 1967, Jan-Mar, 5 folders (Box 18A)
  - 1967, Apr-Sep, 6 folders (Box 19)
  - 1967, Oct-Dec, 3 folders (Box 20)
  - 1968, Jan-Apr, 4 folders (Box 20)
  - 1968, May-Dec, 2 folders (Box 21)
  - 1969 (Box 21)
  - Undated (Box 21)
- Organizational files
  - Administrative files
    - Board of directors meeting reports
      - 1951 (Box 22)
      - 1953, Jun 4-6, Nov 16-17; 2 folders (Box 22)
      - 1954, May 16 (special), Nov 12-14; 2 folders (Box 22)
      - 1955, Mar 5 (special), Nov 17-18; 2 folders (Box 22)
      - 1956, Jun 30-Jul 1 (special), Sep 8 (special), Nov 11; 3 folders (Box 22)
      - 1957, Mar 7 (special), Nov 10; 2 folders (Box 22)
      - 1958, Mar 4-7, Nov 15-16; 2 folders (Box 22)
      - 1959, Mar 3-4, Oct 4 (special committee on broadening the base of private support for higher adult education), Nov 7-8; 4 folders (Box 23)
      - 1960, Mar 12-13, Jul 24-25, Dec 3-4; 3 folders (Box 23)
      - 1961, Mar 11-12, Nov 4-5; 2 folders (Box 23)
      - 1962, Mar 9-11, Nov 3-4; 2 folders (Box 24)
      - 1963, Mar 9-10, Jun 14 (special), Sep 26 (special committee on affiliation), Oct 26-27; 4 folders (Box 24)
      - 1964, Mar 12, Oct 31, Dec 14; 3 folders (Box 24)
      - 1965, Mar 10, Nov 20; 2 folders (Box 24A)
      - 1966, Mar 16, Oct 29, Dec 14; 3 folders (Box 24A)
      - 1967, Mar 20, Sep 15-16, Dec 17-18; 4 folders (Box 24A)
    - Meetings
      - Agendas and Programs
        - 1950-1958 (Box 25)
        - 1959-1960 (Box 25)
        - 1961-1962 (Box 25)
        - 1963-1964 (Box 25)
        - 1965-1966 (Box 25)
        - 1967 (Box 25)
        - Undated (Box 25)
      - Lists of Participants
        - 1954-1960 (Box 25)
        - 1961-1962 (Box 26)
        - 1963-1965 (Box 26)
        - 1966-1968 (Box 26)
    - Memoranda
      - Index, 1953-1963 (Box 26)
      - 1951-1954 (Box 26)
      - 1955 (Box 26)
      - 1956 (Box 26)
      - 1957, 2 folders (Box 27)
      - 1958, 2 folders (Box 27)
      - 1959, 3 folders (Box 28)
      - 1960, 3 folders (Box 28)
      - 1961, 3 folders (Box 29)
      - 1962, 3 folders (Box 29)
      - 1963, 2 folders (Box 30)
      - 1964, 2 folders (Box 30)
      - 1965 (Box 30)
      - 1966 (Box 30)
      - 1967 (Box 31)
      - Undated (Box 31)
    - Personnel data
      - A-W, 3 folders (Box 31)
      - A-K (Box 31)
      - L-W (Box 32)
    - Reports
      - Annual reports
        - To the State of Illinois, 1953-1964 (Box 32)
        - Printed annual reports, 1956-1958 (Box 32)
        - To the Fund for Adult Education, 1961-1965 (Box 32)
        - Semi-annual report to to the Fund for Adult Education, 1965 (Box 32)
        - Annual report to foundations, 1967 (Box 32)
        - To the Commonwealth of Massachusetts, 1961-1965 (Box 32)
      - Board of directors reports
        - Interim reports to the Fund for Adult Education, 1952-1954 (Box 32)
        - Interim reports to the Fund for Adult Education, 1955-1957 (Box 32)
      - Conference reports
        - Conference, 1954; 2 folders (Box 33)
        - Conference, 1955 (Box 33)
        - Conference, 1956 (Box 33)
        - NUEA business meeting, 1966 (Box 33)
    - Staff files
      - Committee on Staff and Personnel, 1958-1959 (Box 33)
      - Consultation and field work, 1964-1967 (Box 33)
      - "Staff Focus", 1967 (Box 33)
      - Monthly field reports, 1964 (Box 33)
      - Notes by A. A. Liveright, undated (Box 33)
      - Notes by Peter Siegle, undated (Box 34)
      - Notes by J. B. Whipple, undated (Box 34)
      - Notes by other staff members, undated (Box 34)
      - Notes on "Teaching the Liberal Arts to Adults", ca. 1955 (Box 34)
      - Office procedures and job descriptions, 1956-1967 (Box 34)
      - Resolution on retirement plan, 1961 (Box 34)
      - Staff assignments, 1954-1965 (Box 34)
      - Staff meeting minutes, 1951-1967 (Box 34)
      - Staff members, 1951-1963 (Box 34)
  - Financial records
    - Accounts receivable and payable journal
      - 1961-1964 (Box 34)
      - 1964-1967 (Box 34)
      - 1967-1968 (Box 34)
    - Auditor's reports, 1958-1964 (Box 34)
    - Bank signature authorizations, 1961-1962 (Box 34)
    - Bank statements
      - 1963 (Box 34)
      - 1964 (Box 34)
    - Budgets
      - 1953-1961 (Box 35)
      - 1962-1965 (Box 35)
      - 1966-1969 (Box 35)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 35)
    - Cash disbursements journal
      - 1962 (Box 36)
      - 1963 (Box 36)
    - Cash receipts journal, 1962 (Box 36)
    - Compensation vouchers, 1964-1968 (Box 36)
    - Financial statements
      - 1951-1959 (Box 36)
      - 1960-1962 (Box 37)
      - 1963-1964 (Box 37)
        See also Package 1
      - 1965-1968 (Box 37)
        See also Packages 2-11
    - Grants made to organizations, 1957-1959 (Box 37)
    - Income tax, 1952-1964 (Box 37)
    - Insurance policies, 1953-1964 (Box 37)
    - Investment of Center funds, memorandum, 1962 (Box 37)
    - Payroll
      - 1961 (Box 38)
      - 1962 (Box 38)
      - 1963 (Box 38)
      - 1964 (Box 38)
        See also Package 12
      - 1965 (Box 38)
        See also Packages 13 and 14
      - 1966 (Package 15) (Box 38)
      - 1967 (Package 16) (Box 38)
      - 1968 (Package 17) (Box 38)
    - Payroll checks (Package 18), 1963-1964 (Box 38)
    - Petty cash, 1962-1968 (Box 38)
    - Staff salaries, 1951-1963 (Box 38)
    - Legal Records
      - Agreement with Macmillian Company, 1961 (Box 39)
      - Agreement with the University of Michigan, 1959 (Box 39)
      - Articles of dissolution, Illinois and Massachusetts, 1968 (Box 39)
      - Articles of incorporation in Massachusetts and agreement of association with Boston University, 1964 (Box 39)
      - By-laws, 1952-1964 (Box 39)
      - Certificates of registration of claims to copyright, 1952-1968 (Box 39)
      - Conditions of transfer of CSLEA publications to Syracuse University, 1968 (Box 39)
      - Memo of understanding between Boston University and CSLEA, 1964 (Box 39)
      - Opinion in the case of Dr. A. A. Liveright v. Joint Committee of the General Assembly of the State of Tennessee, 1968 (Box 39)
  - Project files
    - Administrator Attitude Study, 1959; 1960,; 1961; 3 folders (Box 40)
    - "Adult Education: A New Imperative for Our Times," report of its public reception, 1962 (Box 40)
    - Adult education agencies, report of conference with representatives of, 1960 (Box 40)
    - Adult Education Planning Project, Advisory Committee, Commonwealth of Massachusetts, 1967-1968 (Box 40)
    - Adult learning projects, Allen Tough's study, 1967 (Box 40)
    - Adult motivation and programming, preliminary proposal for research, ca., 1967 (Box 40)
    - Adult Education Association
      - Establishment of a national clearinghouse of adult education, 1960 (Box 40)
      - Labor Education Section, "Workers' Education in the United States", undated (Box 40)
      - Residential Adult Education Committee, 1958-1961 (Box 40)
    - AEA-NUEA Continuing Committee on Urban Life, 1960-1963 (Box 40)
    - American policies and practices on advanced placement and advanced standing procedures, Maurice Needham's "College Without Classes," draft, 1958 (Box 40)
    - Agriculture and home economics cooperative extension work, Commonwealth of Massachusetts, 1965-1967 (Box 40)
    - Air Force Special Degree Programs Conferences, 1962-1963 (Box 41)
    - Armed forces off-duty education programs, review and evaluation, 1967 (Box 41)
    - Arts and sciences deans program, proposal, 1962 (Box 41)
    - Arts Project
      - General, 1957-1964 (Box 41)
      - Audience Education Project, 1966 (Box 41)
      - Building a Cultural Program for Adult Students, draft, 1967 (Box 41)
      - New theater and adult education, 1965 (Box 41)
      - Survey of presenters of art in Syracuse, New York, undated (Box 41)
      - University of Chicago, Fine Arts Program, University College, 1958 (Box 41)
    - AUEC
      - Committee on Liberal Education, 1956-1960 (Box 41)
      - Committee reports, 1951-1965 (Box 41)
      - Leadership Workshop annual confereces
        - 1954-1956 (Box 41)
        - 1957-1958 (Box 42)
        - 1963 (Box 42)
    - AUEC-CSLEA Committee on Future Directions in the Evening College, 1962-1965 (Box 42)
    - AUEC-CSLEA Committee on Future Tasks of the Evening College, 1962 (Box 42)
    - AUEC-NUEA joint meeting, Committee on Minimum Data and Definitions, 1963 (Box 42)
    - AUEC-NUEA statistical report form, 1964 (Box 42)
    - Beloit College, proposals on adult education, 1958-1959 (Box 42)
    - Boston Center for Adult Education, 1965-1967 (Box 42)
    - Boston Public Schools, proposal for study of the new role of the school in the urban community, 1965 (Box 42)
    - Boston University, 1958-1960 (Box 42)
    - Boston University Committee for Adult Education, 1958 (Box 42)
    - Boston University goals for continuing education, 1967 (Box 42)
    - Boston University graduate program in urban affairs, 1968 (Box 42)
    - Boston University proposal for CSLEA, draft, 1957 (Box 42)
    - Boston University, university council meetings, 1964-1967 (Box 42)
    - Boston University Women's Guild, 1965-1966 (Box 42)
    - Boston University Workshop in Planning and Administration of Higher Adult Education, 1965 (Box 42)
    - Brigham Young University, 1963 (Box 42)
    - Brighton Canyon Conference, University Adult Education in the Arts, 1958 (Box 42)
    - Britannica Schools, 1964 (Box 42)
    - Brooklyn College, 1955-1961 (Box 42)
    - Business, Labor, Industry, and Education Conference, 1957 (Box 42)
    - Butler University, 1955 (Box 43)
    - CADESS-CSLEA Seminar on Quality and Validity in University Adult Education, 1960 (Box 43)
    - Careers for women, State University of New York at Farmingdale Evening College, 1966 (Box 43)
    - Carey Study
      - Research proposal, ca., 1957-1958 (Box 43)
      - Draft A, 1959 (Box 43)
      - Draft B, 1959 (Box 43)